One hallmark of writing any code in any app
is to protect the code as much as possible.
To do so, we want to, when necessary, not have
SQL statements written directly in apps, such as
C#-based apps, for example. One can
accomplish this by creating and executing
a stored procedure. A stored procedure is a saved
query, but unlike a view, it can accept both input
and output parameters. Let's take a look at this
stored procedure. It still has a SELECT statement,
just like a view does, but the similarities to
a view stop there. This process does start with
the CREATE PROCEDURE statement. Then look at
these two items with at symbols (@). These are
used as parameters, which are values that pass
through a query. The EmployeeID parameter is an
input parameter. How do we know this? It is not
specified as an output parameter, so the employee
ID is something a person will need to input when
executing this stored procedure. The DepartmentID
parameter is an output parameter. These parameters
are used in apps to return a value the app will
then use later. The SELECT statement says that we
want to select the DepartmentID as a parameter,
an output parameter, from the
EmployeeDepartmentHistory table, where
the BusinessEntityID is equal to the EmployeeID
parameter, the input that we specified. If someone
were to execute this stored procedure and enter
16 for an Employee ID, the query would return the
employee's department. All that said, an output
parameter does not show the DepartmentID here.
Rather, the output parameter determines the order
in which outputs are sent to the app. If there are
multiple outputs, output one will be sent to an
app first, followed by output two, and so on. I
will run this code to build the stored procedure.
Then, I will select and run this EXEC statement,
which executes the code. We get a message
that the command was completed successfully,
but no results show because they
are meant to be used within an app.